<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" media="screen" href="../docbook-html.xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" media="print"  href="../docbook-fo.xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<article class="techreport">
	<title>FieldWorks Database Port</title>
	<subtitle>Project Overview</subtitle>
	<articleinfo>
		<releaseinfo>$Revision$</releaseinfo>
		<pubdate>$Date$</pubdate>
		<author>
			<firstname>Neil</firstname>
			<surname>Mayhew</surname>
			<affiliation>
				<jobtitle>Linux Development Manager</jobtitle>
				<orgname>SIL Language Software Development</orgname>
			</affiliation>
			<email>neil_mayhew@sil.org</email>
		</author>
	</articleinfo>

	<section id="introduction">
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>FieldWorks (<acronym>FW</acronym>) is a suite of applications for linguistics and
			translation. It is built using a common infrastructure, which includes a database with
			an object-relational mapping layer. All data are modelled as objects and persisted in
			the database.</para>
		<para>Currently, FieldWorks uses Microsoft SQL Server (<acronym>SS</acronym>) as its
			database. We are porting FW to use the open-source Firebird database
			(<acronym>FB</acronym>) as a replacement for SQL Server. This is in support of our
			efforts to port FW to Linux and Mac, since Firebird is cross-platform, but may also have
			advantages for the Windows version of FW. We do not plan to maintain multiple versions
			of FW for different databases.</para>
		<para>The porting work touches on three main areas of FieldWorks:</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para><firstterm>DbAccess</firstterm>: a database interface layer, implemented in
					C++, that forwards SQL queries to the database, and retrieves results, using
					native database APIs.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><firstterm>Stored procedures</firstterm>: FW uses over 17,000 lines of SQL in
					the form of stored procedures, views and triggers.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><firstterm>Embedded queries</firstterm>: over 750 SQL queries are spread
					throughout the FW source code. Some of these are confined to the object cache
					modules that provide object persistence, but others occur where the object cache
					is bypassed to increase performance, for example when large tables need to be
					searched and joined.</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		<para>DbAccess is almost finished, the stored procedures are partially done, and not much
			work has been done on the embedded queries. Current efforts are focussed on the stored
			proedures.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="architecture">
		<title>Database Architecture</title>
		<para>FW uses a custom object-relational mapping layer on top of its relational database. In
			addition, the bulk of the schema is machine-generated from object-oriented data models.
			As a result, the organization and naming of tables within the database is very different
			from a typical hand-crafted, purely relational database, which can be quite confusing at
			first for someone experienced in database design and programming.</para>
		<para>The database generaration and operation involves the following stages:</para>
		<section>
			<title>Object Modelling</title>
			<para>Classes to represent all the data that FW uses are modelled using a UML tool
				called MagicDraw. These object models have been developed and refined over many
				years, with extensive input from domain experts in linguistics, translation,
				anthropology and other academic discipines.</para>
			<para>The resulting objects are highly interconnected. Relations between objects are
				characterised by whether they are <firstterm>owning</firstterm> or
					<firstterm>reference</firstterm> properties, and by their
				<firstterm>cardinality</firstterm> (atomic, or belonging to one of several types of
				collections). Owning properties delete their sub-objects when the parent object is
				deleted, but reference properties do not. All relations are reversible (two-way).</para>
			<para>MagicDraw saves its models using an XML schema called XMI, and the model files are
				passed through an XSLT stylesheet to produce a FW-specific XML format called a
					<firstterm>Conceptual Model</firstterm>. This groups classes into modules, and
				defines properties within classes. Properties can be basic (integer, string, etc.)
				or one of the several types of relations already mentioned.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Code Generation</title>
			<para>The Conceptual Model files are passed through a process called <firstterm>Code
					Generation</firstterm>. This turns the model into SQL code that creates in a
				database schema that implements the model.</para>
			<para>Previously, this process has been performed by a custom C++ tool called
					<command>CodeGen</command>. However, as a part of the port, this tool has been
				replaced by an XSLT stylesheet.</para>
			<para>The SQL code that is generated is not DDL to create tables, however. It is a
				series of <code>INSERT</code>s into <firstterm>Metadata Tables</firstterm>. For
				every module, class or property in the model there is one row in the
				<code>MODULE$</code>, <code>CLASS$</code> or <code>FIELD$</code> table respectively.
				The definition of application data tables, columns and views is performed by
				triggers on these Metadata Tables. At database initialization time, when the product
				is first installed, the metadata tables are almost the only tables that are defined.
				The rest of the system is bootstrapped by the triggers in response to
				<code>INSERT</code>s on their respective tables.</para>
			<para>Trigger operation is described in more detail in the following sections.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Table Generation</title>
			<para/>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>View Generation</title>
			<para/>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Object Access</title>
			<para/>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Object Queries</title>
			<para/>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Stored Procedures</title>
			<para/>
		</section>

	</section>

	<section id="methodology">
		<title>Porting Methodology</title>
		<para/>
	</section>

	<section id="glossary">
		<title>Glossary</title>
		<glosslist>
			<glossentry>
				<glossterm>FieldWorks (<acronym>FW</acronym>)</glossterm>
				<glossdef>
					<para>A suite of applications for linguistics and translation based on a common
						infrastructure.</para>
				</glossdef>
			</glossentry>
			<glossentry>
				<glossterm>Firebird (<acronym>FB</acronym>)</glossterm>
				<glossdef>
					<para>A cross-platform, open-source relational database; formerly a commercial
						product from Borland known as Interbase.</para>
				</glossdef>
			</glossentry>
			<glossentry>
				<glossterm>SQL Server (<acronym>SS</acronym>)</glossterm>
				<glossdef>
					<para>A market-leading relational database from our friends in Redmond.</para>
				</glossdef>
			</glossentry>
		</glosslist>
	</section>

</article>
