<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" media="screen" href="../docbook-html.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<article class="techreport">
	<title>Firebird Support Stored Procedures</title>
	<articleinfo>
		<releaseinfo>$Revision$</releaseinfo>
		<pubdate>$Date$</pubdate>
	</articleinfo>
	<section id="Intro">
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>Several stored procedures with a stored procedure name prefix of "spx" are present to
			support the maintenance of Firebird database object. Firebird has numerous rules before
			an object can be dropped or modified. Dependencies have to be dropped before the object
			is dropped or under certain cases even modified. There are no object cascade delete
			options in Firebird. You can have cascade delete between the parent table data and the
			child table data but for example you cannot delete a table that has indexes before you
			delete the indexes manually first.</para>
		<para>Initially only information not immediately apparent from the source code will be
			described here. For example the calling signatures (what parameters to pass and the
			return value if any) will not be described.</para>
		<para>The "drop all" spx procedures are mainly present to help manually wipe out a database
			quickly.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="spx_Stored_Procedures">
		<title>spx Stored Procedures</title>
		<section id="spx_Create_Or_Alter_Exception">
			<title>spx_Create_Or_Alter_Exception</title>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>This procedure will allow you to create or modify a Firebird exception
						object.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>No dependencies are involved.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>
		<section id="spx_Drop_Dependencies">
			<title>spx_Drop_Dependencies</title>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>This procedure will drop all dependent objects that would prevent the
						modifications or deletion of the reference object. </para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>It is used by numerous other "spx" procedures.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>The procedure is recursive and calls upon itself to effectively do a
						cascade delete of all dependent objects.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>
		<section id="spx_Drop_External">
			<title>spx_Drop_External</title>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>This procedure will drop the specified UDF and all dependent
					objects.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Caveat: there is a comment in this procedure that indicates that the
						dependency dropping doesn't work. This has to be looked into in detail
						later.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>
		<section id="spx_Drop_Table">
			<title>spx_Drop_Table</title>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>This procedure will drop the specified table and all dependent
					objects.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>
		<section id="spx_Drop_Generator">
			<title>spx_Drop_Generator</title>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>This procedure will drop the specified generator and all dependent
						objects. A generator is the equivalent of a sequence in Oracle
					databases.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>
		<section id="spx_Valid_New_Constraint_Name">
			<title>spx_Valid_New_Constraint_Name</title>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Main purpose currently is to determine an appropriate constraint name that
						is unique when records are inserted into Class$. The trigger
						T_BI1_Class$_Ins of Class$ calls this procedure.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>This procedure will determine a name within 31 characters that will be
						unique.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>It automatically generates foreign keys, primary keys and
					T_BU5_..._TStmp</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>
		<section id="spx_Drop_All_Tables">
			<title>spx_Drop_All_Tables</title>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>This procedure will drop all of the tables and all dependent
					objects.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>This is currently not called by the build script.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>
		<section id="spx_Drop_All_Exceptions">
			<title>spx_Drop_All_Exceptions</title>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>This procedure will drop all of the exceptions and all dependent
					objects.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>This is currently not called by the build script.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section id="spx_Obsolete">
		<title>Obsolete spx Stored Procedures</title>
		<para>The following stored procedures exist in the source code but aren't used within the
			FieldWorks Firebird database. They were created while trying to port the MSSQL objects
			and code and weren't required by the final code. The source code is kept in case they
			are needed in the future.</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><simpara>spx_Valid_Name</simpara></listitem>
			<listitem><simpara>spx_Valid_New_Name</simpara></listitem>
			<listitem><simpara>spx_Valid_New_NonColumn_Name</simpara></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>
</article>
